[Music]
Good evening. Um, we had a little slight
change of plans. Uh, Mr. Wolfinger's
feeling under the weather. So, I'm going
to run the finance meeting for this
evening. Everybody has their agenda.
We'll get right into it with temporary
resolution 5825
coming through safety committee. A
resolution to appropriate the
unencumbered balance. Amend certificate
appropriations with the county otter and
the law enforcement block jack grant
police fund and approve of then
announced certificate. Uh Mr. Bisjack.
Uh thank you, Mr. Chair. Once again,
this uh legislation is appropriating
about $23,000 to cl out close out the
2022 uh and 2023 JAG grant funds. Uh
yeah, JAG grant funds. Um and this is
for the purpose of trying to get uh
well, not trying, but this is for the
purpose of getting new uh body cameras
for our police officers and issuing a
dispersement to the sheriff's office.
Chief, am I am I missing anything else
with this?
This will be three readings and uh
council member Tiner will be my second.
Okay. Uh 5925
resolution to appropriate
uh this is for
DOJ equitable sharing fund for grant
match dollars for major crimes also
through safety committee. Uh thank you
Mr. Chair. Uh MCU is requesting $40,000
for a uh grant match um that they're
currently pursuing. Uh currently the
Langster Police Department is the
fiduciary on the account. Now I do want
to emphasize that this account is a
shared asset forfeite account and no
taxpayer dollars go into this account.
But due to the fact that uh LPD is the
fiduciary on this account um this
legislation and this appropriation needs
to go through city council and go
through that legal channel. And uh
council member Sie will be my second.
We're going three readings.
Chief, anything? Unless there's
questions. Any questions?
I'll ask. So,
the matching funds are just coming from
LPD.
So, theoretically, yes, there we're the
fidiciary, but the funding in this
account comes from DEA seizures, which
we are part of a conglomerate of
agencies that comprise major crimes
unit. Okay.
Any other questions?
No,
thank you.
Oh, three in a row. 6025 resolution to
appropriate
uh and 45 police and fire fund levy 2021
for the purchase of four police vehicles
for the police department. Mr. Bisjack.
Uh thank you, Mr. Chair. Uh once again,
uh the police department is asking again
for $179,000
for uh uh for additional cruisers here
from Montro Ford. Uh there was a
previous purchase order that was out,
was unexpectedly closed. Uh now it's
been reopened again. Um but because it's
been reopened, we need to go through the
appropriations process. This has already
been budgeted for and expected. Uh once
again, just going through this formality
of making sure the police uh have the
funds to purchase these cruisers. Uh uh
council member Tiner will be my second
and this will be going through three
readings.
Anything else? Nothing bad to add. You
didn't even need to come. Mr. Biz Shacks
got you down. Any questions? Nope. Okay.
All right. Moving on. Temporary
resolution 6125.
That is to schedule our council meetings
for 2026.
everybody had a chance to look at that
and we have three readings to look at
it. So yeah, please encourage everybody
to look at it and also plan accordingly
with schedules so that we can minimize
the number of meetings that I mean
obviously if somebody has a vacation
we accommodate but you're not excused
Miss Crates. Yes, Mr. Bisjack will be my
second. Okay. Sorry.
Temporary resolution 6225
coming through finance. I guess that's
me today. Yes. Resolution to increase
receipts appropriate from the
unencumbered balance amendment
certificate the county audit fund and to
declare an emergency. So actually going
to turn over to the auditor on this
piece please.
Thank you. Um yes, this is um a close
out of the public transit cash. We had
to leave some, if you remember, recall
um from last year to pay the
unemployment to leave uh cash in there
to get some of those bills paid that
were going from July through December.
Then we got a BWC rebate and then we
also got a PNC credit card rebate. Um,
as well as I believe we're getting um a
since the city has the one of the grants
that they used, it was in the city's
name. Um, the county needs to get those
reimbursements, but the state of Ohio
only will reimburse the city. So, in
conjunction with all those rebates plus
that incoming reimbur grant
reimbursement, I'm just needing to
appropriate those funds. So, once they
come in, we can pay back the county,
give it to the public transit at the
county.
Any questions?
Okay,
that's me. Mr. Als, would you be my
second? I'll do two readings on that
resolution.
Do we have any other resolutions?
No ordinances. We have a few new ones.
Um
and 29
is 30 the same. Hold up. Let's let's do
27 separately. It's for the powers run
for start. Yeah. And then the other
three can be together. Yes. Okay.
Okay. So this one is the only one that's
two readings.
Correct. This is the only one. Um,
wing is going to be my second, but I
will have Stephanie, who's already at
the podium, um, discuss it. I jumped up
two. You're fine. So 2725
is for the fourstar development at
Powers Run. That's up 188. This is 333
homes. Um, this is by far the largest
housing development we've had in in a
long time. Um, so,
um, I wanted to just kind of review what
the what TIFFs are. So, TIFFs stands for
tax increment financing. Um, and it is a
collection of increased property tax
revenue generated by the new
developments. Um and it is used to pay
for public improvements in the district.
So we create a district. So we you know
identify all the parcels that are in
there and the money can only be used in
that district. So it is for public
improvements only which is typically
maintained and owned by the city. Um the
tiffs that we propose are always
non-school tiffs so that we keep the
school whole. The name nonschool always
throws me off, but it's to keep the
schools whole. Um, and these, again,
these proceeds are going to go to
supporting public infrastructure at
those sites. This site is completely
undeveloped, has never been developed.
Um, so, as Kurt Shank has said, we don't
know what we don't know when we're
building 333 houses. So, it'll go to
good use at that site.
I'm sure people have questions. If not,
if we do, but if everyone's fine, we can
discuss 28, 29, and 30
and then ask all our questions together
or would you rather? No, no, that's a
great idea. Can I just say one thing
real quick? Um, these are two different
kind of tiffs and I just want everybody
to be very aware of that. Fourstar
powers run is a developer tiff and then
the other three tiffs are city tiffs. So
they're different kinds of tiffs just to
keep that clear for everybody. Yeah,
thank you. So the next three tiffs are
um specific to obviously two different
districts. The first one is on the west
side. It is the Rockmill Industrial
Park. And this was really spurred by um
I I think we talked about um a foreign
company that is coming in um with an
intention of building of of of
developing 105 acres and creating 75
jobs. That's a um a commitment they're
making to the state. And um we really
believe that it's going to be more than
75 jobs. They have to be um they have to
uh not overpromise. You know, Jobs Ohio
will claw back and so they always are um
they always Thank you. They they ask the
users to be very conservative in those
commitments. So that would be for
manufacturing jobs because they're
coming and it's on Campground Road. We
really need to make improvements to
Campground Road. It's essentially a
township road at this point. Now, the
county is already improving um their
bridge that is on campground road that
was just happens to be scheduled for
this um summer, which is great timing.
And then we need to make improvements on
the rest of the road. So, it will go as
far north as Collins and all the way
down to Fair Avenue. Although further
south on Fair when you get to um
Smurfett Westrock, that has already seen
a lot of improvements. So that may have
minimal improvements. Our estimates um
have been provided by EMH&T and then the
city has reviewed them and was able to
kind of tighten them up. So we're
somewhere in the 5 to7 million um in
proceeds uh or in um in improvements. So
we're responsible for that and we looked
at the tiff proceeds and just tiffing
the 105 acres is not going to get us
anywhere near that amount. Um, and we've
decided to tip the whole park. We still
have undeveloped land. We still have
opportunities where there's going to be
public improvement needs in the in the
park and we're going to um capitalize on
some improvements, some developments
that are taking place in the park so we
can utilize that for public
improvements. Um, the other the second
one is out on the east side where we
have the east side industrial park. Um,
and that will include the LDG apartment
complex that is currently under
construction. We don't have any
identified public improvements that we
need to make right now. However, our
long-term goal is the east side
industrial connector. And I do think um
if I had to choose one thing that we may
see out there in terms of public
improvement, there may be some smaller
projects that will help us align the
roads to be ready for the east side
industrial connector. So expanding we
were really um considering our options
of what could we what could we do that
corner at commerce and commerce and
Corey. Thank you. um what could we do to
kind of get it ready for uh the east
side industrial connector?
Then the third one is what we're calling
a central tip district. That's going to
include the Woda Cooper development on
cells. That's going to include Hunter
Trace on 22. That's going to include the
metro properties that are under
construction um along Columbus and
Election House Road and then also the
Gateway site. And certainly for the
gateway site, we we will see those tiff
um proceeds help us build the garage
that would um be on the development on
the gateway site with the hotel and the
apartments. So those are our um
intentions with those tiffs and uh we do
see those those sites u we see the
potential for a lot of growth at those
at those places.
questions.
None. Mr. Stoen.
So is 20. I just want to make sure I
understand this. So 27 for example, what
is the
this is to build infrastructure,
correct?
And who
who builds the infrastructure? the
developer or the city? The developer.
Okay. So, as I was saying, 27 is a
developer tiff. And so, the developer
builds all of the infrastructure and
then whatever money comes in goes back
to the developer, which is like our to
it's like the Ed Road tiff to some
degree. No, it's not like the Ed Road
tiff. The Ed Road tiff the city paid for
the development and then was reimbursed
from the and is still being reimbured
from the TIFF funds. Yeah. Yeah, let's
move on then to 28, 29 and 30. Then who
pays for those improvements? The city
will pay for those improvements. But
after we have started generating that
revenue. So we'll have that money come
in to the account and then we'll have
some idea of you know what the future
revenue is going to be and how that can
be expended. Well, do you have an
amortization schedule that basically
says I mean she mentioned something 5
to7 million on one of these. So if we're
building out infrastructure into the
tune of five to7 million, that's that's
not going to cover that. We know it's
not going to cover that. Okay. So it's
something more than that. Yes. The
building the roadway will be 5 to7
million and we're not going to collect 5
to7 million in this tiff to immediately
pay for that roadway. There are other
sources sources of revenue that will
come to the city to pay for that. That's
the goal anyway. Yep. Okay. So my
question is what is the what is the city
on the hook to provide as far as
building that infrastructure? All of it.
So we can build whatever we want to
build. This is city money and the city
gets to make that decision. I understand
that.
So in 28 for example, I mean when will
we start building and what will we start
building? And my question would be I
mean when when will we start building
infrastructure for that tiff?
It could take two two to three more
years before we can build the the road.
Um, with just the engineering process,
design, finalizing, exactly how much
it's going to cost. Okay, good. Who pays
for the engineering and all that? It
could be done internally depending on um
the capacity and it could be paid for by
the port authority.
If she gets grants from the state of
Ohio to pay for it, then obviously they
would pay for it. I understand. This is
all speculative. Well, I understand
that. But we're also talking about
millions and millions of dollars of
infrastructure and then the payback
isn't going to come back very quickly.
No, we know that. The point is I just
want to make sure they know that. Okay.
Well, the point the point is for all of
you who didn't ask that question, um
that money is is going to accumulate
somewhere and if we don't capture it
with a tiff, then you don't get any of
it to pay for any of that
infrastructure. So, the goal is whatever
the tiff actually throws off in revenue,
we get to use that money. That's all
there is to it. But if they don't do the
development, we don't have to pay any
money at all. If they don't do the
they're if we don't do any development
that we have to we pay no money. I don't
want we are not doing the development
necessarily. Stephanie's goal is to have
these funds go to roadway improvements
for development that we are hoping will
come. If the development doesn't come,
she's not going to put the money into
the road necessarily unless she has some
other user who is willing to come in and
use that roadway. Maybe she's got
another need someplace else immediately.
The goal is to start generating the
revenue though so we have the ability to
look at what that's going to get us and
to plan to use those funds. Understand
that. I have a question. We are not
necessarily on the hook to do these
projects. No, there's nothing. It's just
collecting. Correct. There is nothing
tying us to doing any of these things
obligated.
Do we have a breakdown of like cost and
revenue like by site and maybe some
examples of I looked through this
earlier and um I'm not sure I'm you know
because there's m we have multiple ones
and I'm okay with these kinds of tiffs
and all that. It's but I I like to see
you know because I mean I could see
where we could get stuck doing bonds and
stuff to have to pay for some of this
and that's what makes me a little Let me
rein this back in real quick. Sorry. So
raising hands and we'll we'll figure
that out. So the what and I want to make
sure that I'm clear what you're asking.
So and what they're saying. So the tiff,
putting the putting those in place now
starts generating the revenue, a savings
account if you will, and then if any of
these projects come to fruition, we have
a source to
go and pull funds from to help pay for
those infrastructure improvements. Yes.
Yes. So So how so how does money start
getting put in here without
any city? My is is help me understand
because in mine for the for the
knowledge I have for tiffs the revenue
that comes in through the tiff is the
difference between the the value of the
land that's undeveloped versus the
developed. If we're not having anybody
develop there is no money coming in
because there is no no difference in
that value. So we will not be generating
revenue to pay for infrastructure.
That's why we're going to tiff the whole
park because there are portions sorry no
you go. There are portions we know are
going to develop. She knows that they
are going to develop based on the plans
that they have right now. So we know
there are going to be developments. We
know they are going to build. And so we
want to capture that because you know
typically a developer comes to us and
says, "Hey, can can we do a tiff?" And
they get the balance. They get that
money, right? But this is the opposite.
They're not asking for that money. And
so we are going to collect it and we are
going to use it for public
infrastructure improvements. Do you know
how many developers are planning to
develop? There are um four prospective
projects where we'll see development and
increased value within this park. Yeah.
Okay. I just didn't I mean because
that's how the revenue is generated is
that it's the difference between the
undeveloped value and the developed
value. You get that that's what the the
revenue is coming in. But we don't have
any idea and any numbers of what that
revenue because the by the sounds of it
unless we're getting grants and doing
other things to help pay for road
improvements and I'm assuming not using
3M levy money, right? No. Um it's just
more of looking at as for council as is
what revenue is going to be generated to
help pay for this because is it going to
be something that we're needing to pay
cash? We're gonna have to wait till that
revenue sits before we That's right. can
pay for it. And that could be 10 years,
15 years out. I I don't know how much
revenue it's going to generate. Sure. We
don't we don't either. So, Mr. Mayor,
Mr. Chairman, if you let me finish, I
won't say anything else. I promise.
Okay. So, my I cut So, well, no, no,
it's okay. Um, so ultimately my when
we're in an up economy, I don't really
I'm not concerned much because people
are going to spend money. My question
would be or my thought would be or my
concern would be to understand the fact
that we're amidst this development and
now we're I guess we've agreed to
they're going to pay us so much to put
in this much infrastructure each time we
put in this infrastructure. Are we made
whole immediately or are we made whole
over time?
If
if we if we don't have enough in the
tiff uh uh bucket at the time that we
need to spend, most likely the port will
backs stop the the the debt that we
would have. Is that what your
legislation says the tip is going to do?
The port authority is going to pay and
move. I'm only asking because like I
said, up economies are good, right? Mhm.
is when we get in a bad economy and a
builder stops building and we already
built the infrastructure. Sure. That's
not the infrastructure we're building.
Exactly. We're not building that
infrastructure. The developer will build
that in infrastructure. We're looking at
roads and highways. Yeah. Sidewalks.
We're not We're looking at public
infrastructure. It's it's a city tip.
The infrastructure we're going to be
building is for the city. It's not going
to be for the developer. They're going
to do their water, sewer lines,
everything on the property. We're not
doing that. That's not what this tip is
proposing. This mayor proposing to
capture the additional the incremental
increases
the incremental increases in real estate
tax that currently will go to
essentially not we won't be able to
capture them unless we have a tiff. We
will build that money up and be able to
improve a campground road for instance
as an example that we currently can't
improve because we don't have the
funding. It would also allow us to use
this money for any project that the
council would approve because there
would have to be legislation for
projects and spending money.
We're not this is a this is a city tiff.
I understand. We are not a devel we are
not developing. Ladies and gentlemen,
the chair is running this meeting. He
will recognize people as they come up.
We can't have the back and forth due to
the recording. Thank The the critical
difference is there is no project
planned to spend this money on currently
other than the idea of campground road
improvements. The city and council will
decide what project to spend this money
on. It'll be set aside in in an account
created by the auditor's office
specifically for its purpose, which is
public improvements that will be decided
upon when these projects come up. they
could be. We're currently not planning
on building a development using tiff
money. We're currently trying to capture
that tiff money to use for development
that we feel as a city and a city
government is needed and necessary.
Campground road is an example of that
project where that road is not going to
see any growth unless it's improved. It
is a township road. The portion that has
been improved improved currently exists
with those improvements because they
were needed for development. Now we have
industrial property sitting aside that
is unlikely to be developed and benefit
the community without improvements. This
is a way of doing that. So that's the
proposal.
When we think about a tiff, I think we
all think about a traditional tiff.
Someone's building Timber. They want to
build the roadway up to River Valley
Highlands specifically designated for
that purpose. Developer tiff, they build
the roadway. They get reimbured over
time. This is a different animal and
hopefully some of that explains the
differences. Um All right. Well, I think
in reality when we hear tiff,
everybody's like, "What is that?" And if
you have to know what it is, it makes
you want to vomit. So because it's too
complicated or it can be complicated but
there's a little bit of obvious
does council have questions.
So
yes go ahead Stephanie would you confirm
my understanding that regardless of
whether it's a it's there are things
that are considered improvements for
those parcels that would improve the
project or the parcels around them. Um
but the ma the the main goal is to
improve those parcels that are included.
Yes ma'am. Thank you. That's all my
questions. All right.
Are they always for 30 years? Yes. So,
so there's no debate you can't reduce
the number of years. It has to be 30
years.
I honestly don't know if you can reduce.
The max is 30 and we've always done 30
because that allows you to capture the
most value. Can we find out over time? I
mean, is it I can find out. Okay. I
don't know why we would want to capture
less value though, less money. That
seems I think I'd want to get paid back
faster and make sure we get paid back. I
know I'm mixing tiffs again. Yeah, we're
not getting p We're not paying anything
back. We're just getting money in. This
is free money basically for us. Mr.
Lockberg. Free money. Um if we're not if
we've get to a situation where we're not
bringing in very much money, has there
been any thought to maybe issuing a bond
some bonds to help increase the revenue?
within the tiff. If we don't have the
money to make the improvements, then we
we would have to find another way to to
to
find the money to make the improvements.
But the goal is that the tiff will
collect enough
so that we don't have to do bonds. If we
had a scenario where we absolutely had
to to make, you know, large public
infrastructure improvements and we
didn't have the money, sure, the port
could do bonds, but we don't anticipate
that happen that we're trying to avoid
that cent by collecting the the
proceeds. Well, to piggyback on um her
question on Christina's question,
uh one of those tiff areas, I think it
was the central tiff has a lot of
different properties scattered around.
Are all of the revenue from all those
properties going to be put into one pot?
No. Or it's individual pots per
property. That's one pot. That's why
even for the central central is one pot.
Yeah. Got it. And so it would be our at
our discretion how that money is used.
Then it could go all to one development
on one property. Sure. Potentially.
Okay.
Yeah.
So would wouldn't a potential developer
I could see an issue with that if you
have all these different parcels
together
if they're spread out, you know, if
somebody's looking to develop and
they're going to say, "Well, hey, all
this money is not going to go here. It
could go down the road somewhere. How's
this going to help me
with my infrastructure that I need?"
Do you want us to answer that or do you
want us to wait to be recognized? Sorry.
Yeah. Uh,
like I said, the tiffs can give you a
headache, but what we're not we're like
way
uh can if we could back up a little bit.
So, every one of these is we're trying
to
collect some funds
for future development. There's nothing
saying we have to do any of anything
except collect some money.
And then
if a project comes about and we're like,
hey, that's $10 million of public
infrastructure and $10 million hasn't
been collected, then we would have to
sit here and discuss how would we
potentially fund that because we don't
have enough money in these. Is is it
unusual to put all these parcels
together? Right. But may I interject,
Mr. Chairman? Yeah. I think you're
confusing the concept of the first TIFF
versus the other three. The comm the
other three are community tiffs and we
are saying that we are moving forward
with this development tool to allow us
to build sidewalks or other
infrastructure that we may wish. and
it's not necessarily related to a
specific developer or a specific
project. However, there would have to be
a differentiation in the value of the
property in order to collect extra
funds. Is that correct, auditor? Yes.
Okay. So, we wouldn't be necessarily
reliant or worried about whether or not
a developer would build on this
particular piece of property versus this
one. I think what they're trying to do
is collect areas of the city in the last
one, the central community one where
they know that development might take
place in the future because we've
already we're already seeing people
think about that. What were the parcels
that were in that one? Stephanie,
hold on. Got to scroll. Sorry, I was on
the first one.
I mean, I do understand that. I'm just
Is it odd to lump these together like
that? Have we ever done that before?
That's That's how they're always done.
You have to put them all together. You
couldn't have an individual tiff for
each parcel. That would be like I mean
if they were real close together I could
see lumping them together. But aren't
some of these spread out across town
from each other? Well, that's why we did
an a west side, a central and an east
side, right? Because there's a central
portion of Lancaster and then those two
industrial parks and the industri the
east and the west were made to capture
everything over by the industrial parks
essentially. Okay. It may be a
misunderstood thing that was said
earlier. It sounded like there was a
couple that were kind of spread out. So,
yeah, they're not necessarily close to
each other inside of the city limits,
but they are in the central portion of
the city as opposed to being on the east
side or the west side in the industrial
parks. Does that make sense? Yeah, that
makes sense. Okay. Thank you. Any other
council member have any questions before
I move back to the auditor?
Auditor Nettles. And correct me guys if
I'm wrong on the what for clarification
the powers run is totally different
because you're dealing with single
family homes. It's not the other three
that is almost industrial in that like
for that that one will be on a case by
cases correct. Is it supposed to be 300
homes? 333 333 homes which will almost
be like 333 separate little tiffs based
upon each little value of the house and
the difference. Is that correct? That
was my understanding.
No, that's why there are five TIFF
incentive districts in Powers Run. If
you see if you look at the Powers Run
TIFF, it's different in that get how
they're going to how the that tiff is
going the difference between it's not
going to be the same thing as building a
a manufacturing building to get the same
like there's a parcel that has a
different here's the value of that
parcel versus here because that's kind
of how the tiffs run the different the
land value versus in that different
spread. Each house is going to have a
different That's correct. Yes. value in
each one's going to be ticked off
differently, right? Ticked off
different. Well, that increase in the
increment is Yep.
Everybody else good for now? Yeah. Back
to you, Miss
Did you say back to me? So, we're doing
So, these three are going to be three
readings.
And so, do you want my seconds? Nope,
you're good. All right. Okay.
So, obviously, we have a few more weeks
to come up with any additional questions
um for everyone on those. So,
I thought I was going to have a record
meeting. I was like,
and then I messed that one up. So, I
didn't knock on wood or anything. And
here we are. So, we are up to
departmental updates. Any departmental
updates? Chief, you don't want to come
talk because he stole your thunder.
Okay. Yes, Miss Hall. Sorry. Just wanted
to give you all an update. So, um, the
police chief and I worked together to
get the ownership information for the
alcohol permite that we spoke about at
your last council meeting. Um, there was
there was one issue locally. um that the
chief was able to sus out a little bit.
Um but based on that, we really don't
have the standing to object. Uh and so
the uh clerk sent out the letter on your
behalf today um and the mayor's behalf
not objecting to the issuance of that
permit. So just want everybody to know.
See no department updates uh tonight's
meeting prep. We have none this evening.
Any other items for finance?
We'll take a motion to adjurnn. So
moved,
Mr. Stalling. Second. Second. And we are
adjourned. It is 6:36.
We'll convene tonight's uh regular city
council meeting promptly at uh
6:45.
[Music]
Hi, this is Tracy Kelly, executive
director of the Fairfield Medical Center
Foundation. We are delighted that
Buckeye Toyota and Buckeye Honda have
once again reached out to offer their
support through the Buckeye Cares
program. This month, Buckeye Cares will
make a generous donation to Fairfield
Medical Center with every car they sell.
Please consider the Buckeye family of
dealerships for all of your automotive
needs. Thank you, Buckeye, for all of
your continued generous support.
The Frankie Smith Funeral Home and
Crematory in Lancaster and the Johnson
Smith Funeral Home in Baltimore have a
long and wonderful history of serving
our community. Feel free to give us a
call at 74-653652.
Stop in and see us at either of our two
locations, 405 North Columbus Street in
Lancaster and 207 South Main Street in
Baltimore. Respect for tradition, regard
for change.
[Music]
rise if able and join me in a moment of
prayer. God grant us the serenity to
accept the things that we cannot change,
the courage to change the things we can,
and finally the wisdom to know the
difference. Please join me in the pledge
of allegiance.
I pledge algiance to the flag of the
United States of America and to the
republic for which it stands. One nation
under God, indivisible, with liberty and
justice for all.
I now call the June 23rd, 2025 regular
meeting of city council to order.
We'll now have the reading and disposing
of the journ.
Regular meeting minutes dated June 9th,
2025.
Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the journal. Second.
All those in favor, please signify by
saying I. I. I. I. All those uh opposed,
same sign.
And we'll hop back. We apologize we
didn't do roll call. Would you please do
the roll call? Mr. Als here. Mr. Bisjack
here. Mrs. Kates here. Mrs. Hoop here.
Mr. Lockenberg here. Mr. Skunberg here.
Mr. Sully here. Ms. Teter here. Mr. Wing
here. And Mr. Wolfinger went homesick.
Mr. President, would like to make a
motion to excuse Mr. Wolfinger. Second.
A motion. Second. Uh, excuse council
member Wolfinger. All those in favor
signify by saying I. I. I. All those
opposed, same sign.
We'll now move to the reports of city
officials. I have five of them. Email
data June 10th, 2025 regarding April and
May 2025 income tax revenue reports
responded or um I'm sorry, submitted by
tax commissioner Amy Hamilton. Email
dated June 12th, 2025 regarding mayoral
appointment to N to the NCA. Submitted
by law director Hall, Stephanie Hall.
Email dated June 17, 2025. Lancaster
Fire Department strategic plan 2025
through 2020, 2030.
Submitted by Fire Chief Slate Schultz,
emailed it in TIFF. Ordinances 2825,
2925, and 3025. submitted by law
director Hall.
Mr. President, I like to make a motion
to receive and file the reports of city
officials. Second. We have a motion and
second to receive and file the report to
city officials. All those in favor,
please signify by saying I. I. All those
opposed, saying. We'll now move on to
communications. I have one email dated
June 13, 2025 regarding a concerned
citizen on the state of the country.
Submitted by Jessica Byer.
Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the communication.
Second. Have a motion, second to receive
and file the communication. All those in
favor, please signify by saying I. I.
All those opposing sign. No special
awards or present or special
presentations or awards this evening.
Uh, petitions and memorials. There are
no petitions or memorials this evening.
Thank you. We've now reached the point
in our agenda for permission. identify
yourself for the record and you would
have three minutes.
Thank you. Good evening, council
president, council members, uh, mayor,
and other city officials. I appreciate
the opportunity to speak to you tonight.
Uh, my name is Brian Everett. I live at
201 South High Street. I'll stop signing
in or I I will write what I am saying.
Um, I just wanted to say briefly that
um, as a citizen of the community, I
care about certain things in our
community and there are certain things
in our community that don't bother me,
nor do I care about I don't care about
drag shows, nor do I care about church
services that are held in the public
square. I don't care about the exercise
of rights granted under Constitution for
the exercise of free speech. Um, and I
don't think that's a purview of city
council. I appreciate the robust
conversation about TIFFs because I think
the role of city council is to get to
the business of running a city. I care
about pedestrian and uh cyclist safety.
I care about uh our infrastructure
improving and maintaining our
infrastructure. And I care about making
this community a place where people are
safe, comfortable, and excited to live,
work, and play. So, I appreciate you uh
as you all work towards that common
goal. Thank you.
Thank you.
Is there anybody else who wishes to
address council this evening?
Seeing none, we thank you for attending.
Now move to the reports of standing
committees. I have six. I have finance
committee meeting minutes dated June
9th, 2025. Submitt submitted by Mr.
Wolfinger. Water water pollution
committee agenda dated June 11th 2025
submitted by Mr. Wing. Service committee
meeting agenda June dated June 12th,
2025 submitted by Mr. Als. Water
pollution committee minutes dated June
13, 2025 submitted by Mr. Wing. Finance
agenda or finance committee agenda dated
June 19th, 2025 submitted by Mr.
Wolfinger. Hello committee minutes dated
June 22nd submitted by Mrs. Kurtz.
Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive file the reports of standing
committees. Second. We have a motion and
a second to receive and file the reports
of standing committees. All those in
favor, please signify by saying I. I.
All those opposed, same sign. Reports of
special committees. There are no
reports. There are no public hearings
scheduled for this evening. We will now
move on to the reading of resolutions.
Beginning with the third reading of
resolutions, temporary resolution 4925,
a resol a resolution to increase
receipts appropriate from the
unencumbered balance. Amend the
certificate of other sources and
appropriations with the county auditor
and the general fund
for the one-time strategic community
investment grant program and to declare
an emergency. This is through the
finance committee. Mr. Skunover, Mr.
Sully. Council member Skunover. Mr.
President, I'd like to make a motion
that council pass and gross and enter
upon the written record temporary
resolution 4925.
Second have a motion and a second to
pass and engross and enter upon the
written record temporary resolution
4925. Discussion council member Skunar.
I don't have any. Thank you. Any f
hearing? None. Please roll. Mr. Als,
yes. Mr. Bisjack, yes. Mrs. Kra, yes.
Mrs. Hoop, yes. Mr. Luberg, yes. Mr. Mr.
Skover. Yes. Yes. And Mr. W. Yes. Motion
to pass and gross and enter upon the
written record. Temporary resolution 925
passes 9 to zero. Temporary resolution
5025.
A resolution to authorize the service
safety director to dispense with
competitive bidding for a sole source
provider contract for membrane
replacement for the South Water Plant.
This is through water water pollution
committee. Mr. Wing and Miss Tiner.
Council member Wing. Yes, Mr. President.
I'd like to make a motion that council
pass and gross and enter upon the
written record temporary resolution
numbered 50-25. Second. We have a
motion, a second to pass and gross and
enter upon the written record temporary
resolution 5025. Discussion, Council
Member Wing. Yes. This legislation names
a sole source for 800 uh membranes that
we replaced uh for the South Water
Treatment Plant. Thank you. Any further
discussion? Hearing none, please call
the RO. Mr. Als, yes. Mr. Bisjack, yes.
Mrs. Kit, yes. Mrs. Hoop. Yes. Mr.
Lotober. Mr. Skunover. Yes. Mr. Sully.
Yes. 06 for the payment of the from
compensary time. This is through water
water pollution committee. Mr. Wing and
Miss Tener. Council member Wing. Mr.
President, I move that council suspend
its rules and wave the third reading of
temporary resolution number 56-25.
Second. We have a motion in a second to
suspend the rules and wave the third
reading of temporary resolution 5625.
Any discussion on the motion to suspend
council member Win just to be in
compliance with the auditor schedule.
Thank you. Um any further discussion
hearing? None. Please call the roman.
Please call the role. Mr. Als, yes. Mr.
Bishek, yes. Mrs. Kite, yes. Mrs. H.
Yes. Mr. Lockchnner. Yes. Mr. Skoonover?
Yes. Mr. Sully? Yes. Miss Ter? Yes. And
Mr. W? Yes. Motion to suspend the rules
and wave the third reading of temporary
resolution 5625 passes 9 to zero.
Council member Wing. Yes. Thank you, Mr.
President. I'd like to make a motion
that council pass and gross under the
written record temporary resolution
number 56-25.
Second. A motion second to pass and grow
and enter upon the written record
temporary resolution 5625.
Any discussion? Council member W. Yes.
Again, uh this just increases uh that
line item by $2,500
uh to account for um a higher than
expected payout for retirement. Thank
you. Any further discussion? Hearing
none, please call the role. Mr. Als,
yes. Mr. Bisch, yes. Mrs. Kes, yes. Mrs.
Hoop, yes. Mr. Lockenberg, yes. Mr.
Screener, yes. Mr. Sully, yes. Miss
Tiner, yes. And Mr. Wing, yes. Motion
passing and gross and enter upon the
written record. Temporary resolution
5625 passes 9 to zero. Temporary
resolution 5725.
A resolution to authorize the service
safety director to dispense with
competitive bidding and enter into an
agreement to purchase a time TYMCO
model 600 street sweeper from the state
cooperative purchasing program for the
for use by the storm water and
transportation departments. This is
through water water pollution committee.
Mr. Wing and Mr. ALS. Council member
Wing. Mr. President, I move that um
council suspend its rules and wave the
third reading of temporary resolution
57-25.
Second a motion a second to pass or to
uh suspend the rules and wave the third
reading of temporary resolution 5725.
Any discussion on the motion to suspend?
Yes, just there's a nine-month lead time
on uh getting this product delivered and
this is so we can get it in a timely
manner next spring. Thank you. Any
further discussion on the motion to
suspend?
Hearing none, please call the role. Mr.
Als, yes. Mr. Bisjack, yes. Amend the
rules and wave the third reading of
temporary resolution 5725 passes 9 to
zero. Council member Wing. Mr.
President, I move that council pass and
gross and enter upon the written record.
Temporary resolution number 57-25.
Second. Motion second to pass and gross
and enter upon the written record
temporary resolution 5725. Any further
discussion? Council, this I was just
going to add this is a budgeted purchase
to replace a street sweeper that has
ended its useful life. Thank you. Any
further discussion? Hearing none, please
call the role. Mr. Als, yes. Mr.
Bishack, yes. Mrs. Kes, yes. Yes. Mr.
Bishack, yes. Mrs. Kes, yes. Mrs. Hoop,
yes. Mr. Lockenberg, yes. Mr. Skoover,
yes. Mr. Sully, yes. Miss Tiner, yes.
And Mr. Wink, yes.
Motion to pass and engross and enter
upon the written record. Temporary
resolution 5725 passes 9 to zero. We'll
now move on to the first reading of
resolutions beginning with temporary
resolution 5825.
A resolution to appropriate from the
unencumbered balance and amend the
certificate of appropriations with the
county auditor in the law enforcement
block drag grant police fund 2027 and
approve a then and now certificate for
purchases. This is through safety
committee. Mr. Bisjack and Miss Tina.
Council member Bisjack. Thank you, Mr.
President. This is the first of three
readings. First of three readings on
temporary resolution 5825.
Temporary resolution 5925.
A resolution to appropriate from the
undercover balance and amend the
certificate of appropriations with the
county auditor in the DOJ equitable
sharing fund 2048
for grant match dollars for the major
crimes unit. This is through safety
committee. Mr. Bisjack and Mr. Mr.
Sully. Council member Bisjack. Thank
you, Mr. President. This is the first of
three readings. First of three readings
on temporary resolution 5925.
Temporary resolution 6025. A resolution
to appropriate from the unencumbered
balance and amend the certificate of
appropriations with the county auditor
in the 0.45 police and fire levy fund or
levy 2021
fund and fund 2051 for the purchase of
four police vehicles for use by the
Lancaster Police Department. This again
is through safety committee Mr. Bisjack
and Miss Teener. Council member Bisjack.
Uh thank you Mr. President. This is the
first of three readings. First of three
meetings on temporary resolution 6025.
Temporary resolution 6125.
A resolution to schedule Lancaster City
Council meetings and finance committee
meetings for 2026.
Uh this is through law committee. Mrs.
Kates and Mr. Bishek. Council member
Kates. Yes. Thank you. First of three
readings. First readings on temporary
resolution 6125.
Temporary resolution 6225. A resolution
to increase receipts, appropriate from
the unencumbered balance, and amend the
certificate of appropriations with the
county auditor in the public transit
fund 2021 and to declare an emergency.
This is through finance committee, Mr.
Skunover and Mr. Als. Council member
Skunover. That's the first of two
readings, please. First of two readings
on temporary resolutions 6025.
We've reached the reading uh the final
readings of resolutions, and we will now
move to ordinances. Uh, beginning with
the third reading of temporary ordinance
2625,
an ordinance to accept the petition for
the annexation of 0.605
plus or minus acres in the Pleasant
Township to consent to annexation and to
declare an emergency. This is through
Economic Development Committee, Mrs.
Hoop and Mrs. Kra. Council member Hoop.
Um, yes, Mr. President. And I'd like to
make a motion that council pass and
gross and enter upon the written record
temporary ordinance 26-25.
Second. And any discussion, council
member. Um yes. This um property being
annexed was just sold to the developer
and we're just getting rid of the island
that it creates. Thank you. Any further
discussion?
Hearing none, please call the role. Mr.
Als, yes. Mr. Bischek, yes. Mrs. Kates,
yes. Mrs. Hoop, yes. Mr. Mr. Lockenberg.
Yes. Mr. Scooter. Yes. Mr. Sie. Yes.
Miss Tiner. Yes. Mr. Wing. Yes. Motion
to pass. Gross. Enter upon the written
record. Temporary ordinance 2625 passes
9 to zero. There are no second readings
of ordinances this evening. So, we will
move to the first reading of temporary
ordinance 2725.
All I have to say is thank you,
Stephanie. It's a lot to read tonight. I
appreciate that. You're welcome. wasn't
paying attention, but you're very
welcome. An ordinance creating five
incentive districts and declaring
improvements
to certain real property within the
incentive districts to be a public
purpose and exempt from real property
taxation, identifying certain public
infrastructure improvements that once
made will benefit or serve the parcels
in the incentive districts, requiring
the owners of those parcels to make
service payments in lie of taxes.
Establishing an incentive district
public improvement tax increments,
equivalent fund for the deposit of such
service payments, authorizing payments
to the city of
the Lancaster City School District, and
approving related matters. This is
through economic development committee,
Mrs. Wing or I'm sorry, Mrs. Hoop and
Mr. Wing. Council member Hoop. Yes, this
is first of two readings. First of two.
Two. Yeah. Okay. First of two readings
on temporary ordinance 2725.
Temporary ordinance 2825,
an ordinance declaring the improvement
to certain real property located in the
city of Lancaster, Ohio to be a public
purpose declaring such improvement to be
exempt from real property taxation
pursuant to the Ohio Revised Code
section 5709.4B
4B
requiring the owners thereof of to make
annual service payments in lie of taxes.
Describing the public infrastructure
improvements to be made that will
directly benefit the real property.
Establishing a public uh improvement tax
incentive equivalent fund for the
deposit of service payments together
with related authorizations.
Economic development committee, Mrs.
Hoop and Mrs. Right. Council member
Hoop. Um, yes. This is one of first of
three readings. First of three readings
on temporary ordinance 2825.
Temporary ordinance 2925.
An ordinance declaring the improvement
to certain real property located in the
city of Lancaster to be a public purpose
declaring such improvement to be exempt
from real property taxation pursuant to
a higher revised code section 5709.4.
40B requiring the owners thereof to make
annual service payments in lie of taxes
describing the public infrastructure
improvements to be made that will
directly benefit the real property.
Establishing a public improvement tax
increment
uh equivalent fund for the deposit of
service payments together with related
authorizations. This again is through
economic development committee Mrs. Hoop
and Mr. scoot over and declare an
emergency.
Um, council member who this is first of
three readings. First of three readings
on temporary ordinance 2925.
Temporary Ordinance 3025, an ordinance
declaring the improvement to certain
real property located in the city of
Lancaster, Ohio to be a public purpose,
declaring such improvement to be exempt
from real property taxation pursuant to
Ohio Revised Code section 5709.40B
40B requiring the owners there thereof
to make annual service payments in lie
of taxes. Describing the public
infrastructure improvements to be made
that will directly benefit the real
property establishing a public
improvement tax increment equivalent
fund for the deposit of service payments
together with related authorizations.
Um economic development committee Mrs.
Hoop and Mrs. Kates
She removed that. Well, she she removed.
Yeah, they removed declaring an
emergency. Oh, it's still on my Okay.
Oh, council member Hoop. Okay, that's
first of three readings. First of three
readings on temporary ordinance 3025.
We have reached the end of our
ordinances this evening. We have no
tabled legislation.
Unfinished business
hearing. None. New business. I do have
new business. Thank you. Um, Councilman
Wolfinger had provided me with a letter
um that he wanted me to read tonight
during council meeting.
Okay. Yeah. Um, he was proudly elected
into a position at OU and
because of that he can no longer seek
and hold an elected office anywhere
else. So, he asked me to read a letter
to you guys.
Um, on Friday, June 13, 2025, I had the
honor of being appointed the Ohio
University Board of Trustees, which is
the governing board of Ohio University.
As you are aware, my commitment in the
numerous U boards continues to be a very
important part of my life. Needless to
say, this opportunity provides me with
great pride and gratitude, and I
accepted it immediately. When I received
a copy of the resolution of my
appointment, I realized that elected
officials are ineligible to hold this
position. In speaking with the Ohio
University legal council, it was made
clear that I would need to resign from
public office in order to serve on the
Ohio University Board of Trustees. After
a lot of thought and consideration, I've
decided to resign 30th of 2025. I've
enjoyed my tenure of serving the
citizens of Lancaster, fellow council
members, and certainly the city
administration. With kindest regards,
Bob Wolfinger, and then he also provided
the appointment sheet for the regional
trustee
resolution. Thank you.
Uh we will move to the announcement of
scheduled meetings.
Um, I have June 23rd, 2025 at 6:30 p.m.
in council chambers. These are the next
regular sessions of council. Um, July
14th, 2025 at 6:30 um p.m. in again here
in council chambers.
Move to regularly scheduled committee
meetings. I have none.
We don't have any regularly scheduled
committee meetings. I have Oh, I'm
sorry. Did I go back?
I'm sorry. I was looking up at the
special meetings. Okay. I have public
works committee meeting um July 11th at
7:30 a.m. in city hall 1897 conference
room. I have a service committee meeting
um June 13th at 8 a.m. City Hall 1897
conference room. I have water water
pollution control service committee
meeting and July or June 13th at 9:00 am
city hall 1897 conference room. Thank
you. Reading of bills. I have one for
MNCO for $67.92.
Thank you, Mr. President. I would like
to
I would like to make a motion to pay the
bill. Thank you. Second. We have a
motion and second to pay the bill. All
those in favor, please signify by saying
I. I. I. All those opposed, same sign.
Executive session. There is no need. At
this time, I would accept a motion to
adjurnn. Would love to make that motion
we adjourn. And I'd love to second that.
We have a motion and second to adjurnn.
All those in favor, please signify by
saying I. I.
Please remember to sign your
legislation. The next regular meeting of
city council will be July 14th.
That'll be
[Music]
Hi. Hi, this is Tracy Kelly, executive
director of the Fairfield Medical Center
Foundation. We are delighted that
Buckeye Toyota and Buckeye Honda have
once again reached out to offer their
support through the Buckeye Cares
program. This month, Buckeye Cares will
make a generous donation to Fairfield
Medical Center with every car they sell.
Please consider the Buckeye family of
dealerships for all of your automotive
needs. Thank you, Buckeye, for all of
your continued generous support.
The Frankie Smith Funeral Home and
Crematory in Lancaster and the Johnson
Smith Funeral Home in Baltimore have a
long and wonderful history of serving
our community. Feel free to give us a
call at 740-653652.
Stop in and see us at either of our
locations, 405 North Columbus Street in
Lancaster and 207 South Main Street in
Baltimore. Respect for tradition, regard
for change.
[Music]